

□ (+41) 767228375 | antoine.wehenkel@gmail.com | A awehenkel.github.io ■ AWehenkel | ■ @WehenkelAntoine | ► Antoine Wehenkel

### PERSONAL STATEMENT

"We know the past but cannot control it. We control the future but cannot know it." Claude Shannon

Passionate Post-doctoral researcher at Apple, my research targets useful and accurate uncertainty quantification for sensitive tasks, as found in various medical and scientific domains. I design and apply algorithms that leverage domain knowledge in various forms, e.g., equations, numerical simulations, or independence assumptions, for uncertainty quantification in low-data regimes. I am an engineer excited both by the theoretical foundations and real-world impact of Machine Learning.

# **WORK EXPERIENCE**

#### Post-doctoral Researcher

11/2022 - Now

Apple Inc., Health AI Team (Zürich)

Extending simulation-based inference algorithms for biomarkers prediction from full-body hemodynamics simulators. Two papers as first author in preparation and main organizer of SynS & ML at ICML 2023.

Research Intern 11/2021 - 09/2022

Apple Inc., Health AI Team (Zürich)

Physics Informed Machine Learning. A publication as a first author published at TMLR.

Applied Scientist Intern

Summer 2021

Amazon Web Services (remote)

Worked within Codeguru AI team. Defined and developed a project applying deep learning (graph neural networks) to automatic program analysis. Secured an offer for a returning internship.

# **EDUCATION**

Ph.D. student in Machine Learning - *ULiège*, *Liège* 10/2018 - 10/2022 Advisor: Professor Gilles Louppe

Research interests: generative modeling, deep learning and simulation-based inference.

Master in Computer Engineering - *ULiège*, *Liège* 09/2016 - 06/2018

Summa Cum Laude - 88%

Exchange student in the Master in Data Science - EPFL, Lausanne 09/2017 - 06/2018

Average score: 5.8/6 - 97%

Bachelor in Engineering - *ULiège*, *Liège* 09/2013 - 06/2016 Magna Cum Laude - 81%

# PERSONAL RESEARCH PROJECTS

# Automating signal processing with physical simulations

2022 - Now

Antoine Wehenkel - Jörn-Henrik Jacobsen, Jens Behrmann, Ozan Senner, Marco Cuturi

Designing algorithms that leverage numerical simulations to enable accurate uncertainty quantification in low-data regimes. Applications to prediction of cardiovascular biomarkers from non-invasive biosignals.

Research project initiator, 2 first-author papers (in prep.), organizer of the SynS & ML at ICML 2023.

# Deep Learning for inverse problems in Science

2018 - 2022

Antoine Wehenkel - Gilles Louppe

Advancing simulation-based inference by exploring new means for implementing more effectively inductive bias into deep generative models.

Co-authored 7 papers, 3 at top Machine Learning conferences and 4 at workshops (2 spotlights).

# Parameter estimation of transmission lines from synchrophasor measurements

2017 - 2018

Antoine Wehenkel - Arpan Mukhopadhyay, Mario Paolone, Jean-Yves Le Boudec

Estimation of transmission lines parameters noisy phasors measurements with sparse non-convex optimisation.

Graded 6/6 as a master's thesis at EPFL and published in an international journal.

# An algorithmic approach for harvesting renewable energy with electric vehicles Antoine Wehenkel - Antoine Dubois, Raphael Fonteneau, Damien Ernst

2016 - 2017

Development of optimisation algorithms for the integration of Electric vehicle fleets in the electrical network.

This project was done in collaboration with Engle company and led to a scientific publication.

# SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Simulation-based Inference for Cardiovascular Models

Wehenkel A, Behrmann J, Senner O, Miller A, Sapiro G, Cuturi M, Jacobsen JH

Pre-print.

Robust Hybrid Learning With Expert Augmentation

Wehenkel A, Behrmann J, Hsu H, Sapiro G, Louppe G, Jacobsen JH

Transactions on Machine Learning Research, 2023.

Diffusion Priors In Variational Autoencoders

Wehenkel A, Louppe G

Workshop on Invertible Neural Networks, Normalizing Flows, and Explicit Likelihood Models at ICML 2021.

Graphical Normalizing Flows

Wehenkel A, Louppe G

International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS) 2021.

Neural Empirical Bayes: Source Distribution Estimation and its Applications to Simulation-Based Inference Vandegar M, Kagan M, Wehenkel A, Louppe G.

International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS) 2021.

Unconstrained monotonic neural networks

Wehenkel A, Louppe G.

Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS/NIPS) 2019.

Parameter Estimation for Three Phase Untransposed Short Transmission Lines from Synchrophasor Measurements Wehenkel A, Mukhopadhyay A, Le Boudec JY, Paolone M.

IEEE Transactions on Instrumentation and Measurement. 2020 Jan 23.

# **SKILLS**

- Theoretical background: Deep Learning, Machine Learning, Optimisation, and Statistics.
- Programming: Python, Git, Bash, PHP, Javascript, Java, Matlab, C++ and C.
- · Libraries: PyTorch, Scikit-Learn, Numpy, Pandas, D3, Matplotlib.
- · Communication: Technical writing, Latex, HTML/CSS, data vizualization, teaching.
- Languages: French (native), English (professional proficiency).

#### TALKS

• The Symbiosis between Deep Probabilistic and Scientific Models . Gen U 2022, Copenhagen.	09/2022
<ul> <li>Normalizing Flows and Bayesian Networks. CogSys seminar (DTU). Remote.</li> </ul>	10/2020
• Normalizing Flows for Probabilistic Modeling and Inference. Montefiore (ULiège) journal club, Liège.	04/2020
Neural Likelihood-Free Inference. GRAPPA (UvA) journal club, Amsterdam.	10/2019
Unconstrained Monotonic Neural Networks. Benelearn 2019, Brussels.	11/2019

# REVIEWING

- Conferences: PMAPS2020, NeurIPS (2020-21-23), ICLR (2021-22-23), AISTATS (2021-22-23), ICML (2021-22-23).
- Workshops: ML4PS (at NeurIPS, 2020-21-22), EBM (at ICLR, 2021), INNF+ (at ICML, 2021).
- Journals: TMLR (since 2022)

#### **AWARDS**

- Best PhD Thesis award from AIM (2023) 3500€
- Outstanding reviewer award for ICLR2021 Awarded to the top 10% reviewers.
- FNRS Research Fellowship (2018 2022) Around 100 awardees in Belgium each year.
- Best Master's thesis awards from AIM and from AILg (2018) One award for 40 candidates 850€
- Ranked 1<sup>st</sup> the "Kaggle in class" machine learning course competition (ULiège, 2016 and 2018) 64 teams.
- Physics award for outstanding student (2013) One award for more than 150 students.
- Physics award at Belgian Olympiad (2012 and 2013) Top-5 among hundreds of students in Belgium.

# REFEREES

- Gilles Louppe (g.louppe@uliege.be) Ph.D. advisor.
- Jörn-Henrik Jacobsen Manager at Apple.
- Guillermo Sapiro Team leader at Apple.

# References

- [1] Arnaud Delaunoy, Antoine Wehenkel, Tanja Hinderer, Samaya Nissanke, Christoph Weniger, Andrew R Williamson, and Gilles Louppe. Lightning-fast gravitational wave parameter inference through neural amortization. In *Machine Learning and the Physical Sciences Workshop at NeurIPS2020*, 2020.
- [2] Arnaud Delaunoy, Joeri Hermans, François Rozet, Antoine Wehenkel, and Gilles Louppe. Towards reliable simulation-based inference with balanced neural ratio estimation. *Neural Information Processing Systems 2022*, 2022.
- [3] Antoine Dubois\*, Antoine Wehenkel\*, Raphael Fonteneau, Frédéric Olivier, and Damien Ernst. An app-based algorithmic approach for harvesting local and renewable energy using electric vehicles. In *Proceedings of the 9th International Conference on Agents and Artificial Intelligence (ICAART 2017)*, 2017.
- [4] Jonathan Dumas, Colin Cointe, Antoine Wehenkel, Antonio Sutera, Xavier Fettweis, and Bertrand Cornélusse. A probabilistic forecast-driven strategy for a risk-aware participation in the capacity firming market. *IEEE Transactions on Sustainable Energy*, 13(2):1234–1243, 2021.
- [5] Jonathan Dumas, Antoine Wehenkel, Damien Lanaspeze, Bertrand Cornélusse, and Antonio Sutera. A deep generative model for probabilistic energy forecasting in power systems: normalizing flows. *Applied Energy*, 305:117871, 2022.
- [6] Joeri Hermans, Arnaud Delaunoy, François Rozet, Antoine Wehenkel, and Gilles Louppe. Averting a crisis in simulation-based inference. *Transactions on Machine Learning Research*, 2021.
- [7] Joeri Hermans, Arnaud Delaunoy, François Rozet, Antoine Wehenkel, Volodimir Begy, and Gilles Louppe. A crisis in simulation-based inference? beware, your posterior approximations can be unfaithful. *Transactions on Machine Learning Research*, 2022.
- [8] Arthur Pesah\*, Antoine Wehenkel\*, and Gilles Louppe. Recurrent machines for likelihood-free inference. In *MetaLearn Workshop @ NeurIPS2018*, 2018.
- [9] Thibaut Théate, Antoine Wehenkel, Adrien Bolland, Gilles Louppe, and Damien Ernst. Distributional reinforcement learning with unconstrained monotonic neural networks. arXiv preprint arXiv:2106.03228, 2021.
- [10] Maxime Vandegar, Michael Kagan, Antoine Wehenkel, and Gilles Louppe. Neural empirical bayes: Source distribution estimation and its applications to simulation-based inference. In *International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics 2021*, 2020.
- [11] Nicolas Vecoven, Damien Ernst, Antoine Wehenkel, and Guillaume Drion. Introducing neuromodulation in deep neural networks to learn adaptive behaviours. *PloS one*, 15(1):e0227922, 2020.
- [12] Antoine Wehenkel. Inductive Bias In Deep Probabilistic Modelling. PhD thesis, ULiège-University of Liège, Liège, Belgium, October 2022.
- [13] Antoine Wehenkel and Gilles Louppe. Unconstrained monotonic neural networks. In *Neural Information Processing Systems* 2019, volume 33, 2019.
- [14] Antoine Wehenkel and Gilles Louppe. Graphical normalizing flows. In *International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics*, volume 2021, pages 37–45. PMLR, 2020.
- [15] Antoine Wehenkel and Gilles Louppe. You say normalizing flows i see bayesian networks. In INNF+ Workshop @ ICML2020,
- [16] Antoine Wehenkel and Gilles Louppe. Diffusion priors in variational autoencoders. In INNF+ Workshop @ ICML2021, 2021.
- [17] Antoine Wehenkel, Arpan Mukhopadhyay, Jean-Yves Le Boudec, and Mario Paolone. Parameter estimation of three-phase untransposed short transmission lines from synchrophasor measurements. IEEE Transactions on Instrumentation and Measurement, 69(9):6143–6154, 2020.
- [18] Antoine Wehenkel, Jens Behrmann, Hsiang Hsu, Guillermo Sapiro, Gilles Louppe, and Jörn-Henrik Jacobsen. Robust hybrid learning with expert augmentation. *Transactions on Machine Learning*, 2023.
- [19] Antoine Wehenkel, Jens Behrmann, Andrew C Miller, Guillermo Sapiro, Ozan Sener, Marco Cuturi, and Jörn-Henrik Jacobsen. Simulation-based inference for cardiovascular models. arXiv preprint arXiv:2307.13918, 2023.